<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-05T11:49:56+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Embracing and exploring tech world</title><subtitle>Observing life from a software perspective.</subtitle><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Dar es salaam City Drone Imagery</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Drone-Imagery-Viz/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Dar es salaam City Drone Imagery" /><published>2019-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/-Drone-Imagery-Viz</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Drone-Imagery-Viz/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/dar-drone-imagery-viz.png)

_Drone Imagery Map_

## Visualizing Dar es salaam drone imagery

At the end of 2017, The World Bank Tanzania, in collaboration with the Dar Rapid Transit ([DART](https://www.dart.go.tz/)) Agency, 
supported the collection of high-resolution drone imagery across Dar es Salaam. This initiative was part of a broader effort to 
support urban planning and development along the proposed Bus Rapid Transit (BRT) routes throughout the city.

The drone mapping activity successfully captured detailed imagery of all areas surrounding the planned BRT corridors. 
This rich dataset was expected to serve as a critical resource for planning and decision-making throughout
the BRT development process.

However, once the data was collected, the next challenge emerged—visualizing and accessing it effectively. 
The raw drone imagery, provided in GeoTIFF format, was extremely large in size. This made it difficult to load 
and interact with the data on a regular computer. Standard desktop machines often struggled to open the files, 
and even when they did, rendering the imagery was slow.

To make things more complicated, viewing GeoTIFFs typically requires specialized Geographic Information System (GIS) software,
which is often desktop-based and not very user-friendly for non-technical users. This meant that anyone wanting to interact 
with the data had to first install special GIS tools, creating a barrier for planners and the public alike.

These limitations highlighted the need for a more accessible, web-based solution—something that didn’t require 
powerful hardware or dedicated software installation, and could be used directly from a browser.

As a member of The World Bank Tanzania team supporting the DART project, 
I was tasked with developing a visualization tool for this imagery dataset. 
My goal was to make the drone imagery easily accessible to a wide range of users, 
from urban planners to city officials and community members.

Using [Mapbox GL](https://docs.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-js/overview/) I built a lightweight, high-performance web application that could display the
large drone imagery efficiently, directly within a browser window.

The result was a high perfomance and easily accessible web map, it can be viewed [here](http://brt-viz.herokuapp.com/)]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Converting ODK location data to WKT in QGIS</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/ODKTrace2WKT/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Converting ODK location data to WKT in QGIS" /><published>2019-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/-ODKTrace2WKT</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/ODKTrace2WKT/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/odktrace2wkt.png)

_Plugin interface_

## Loading ODK location data in QGIS

[Open Data Kit(ODK)](https://getodk.org/) is now widely used in collecting location data. One notable use case is the project 
called [Ramani Huria](https://ramanihuria.org/) (Open Map) which used ODK to map Dar es salaam city drains. 
One of the challenges in using ODK to collect linestring data is the format that it 
save the data into (geotrace), the format currently is not a standard that is directly supported in most GIS applications.

While ODK supports collecting point and line-based geographic data, the format it uses to store data is not
a widely accepted. 
This has made it difficult for teams to import and work with the data in tools like QGIS after data collection.

Ramani Huria team was faced with this problem and they wrote script that convert the data from geotrace 
to Well-Known text format which is widely used standard. 

The issue with scripts is they are not very user friendly. Recognizing the need for a more accessible solution, 
the Ramani Huria team tasked me with creating a QGIS plugin to simplify this conversion process for everyday users.

I developed a QGIS plugin that helps users to convert the ODK geotrace data into Well-Known text format by building upon the work that Ramani Huria had already started. 
Since the team already had a [script](https://github.com/ivangayton/ODK_geotrace_to_WKT/blob/master/lines_to_wkt.py) written in Python.

The plugin works on all QGIS 3 versions. See the following [how to use video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GvxkoVP0-Dc) on plugin usage instructions.

The plugin is intended to make geospatial data workflows smoother and more accessible, particularly for 
community mapping teams and organizations using ODK in the field. By bridging the gap between mobile data collection 
and GIS analysis, it enables more people to benefit from the power of open mapping tools.

[Plugin repository](https://plugins.qgis.org/plugins/odktrace2wkt/)

[Source code](https://github.com/Samweli/odktrace2wkt)]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using AI in Trash Detection</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/AI-Trash-Detection/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using AI in Trash Detection" /><published>2019-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/AI-Trash-Detection</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/AI-Trash-Detection/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/trash-detector.png)

_Trash detection web application interface_

## Trash detection from mapping images

During the trash mapping activity [here](http://samweli.github.io/Trash-Map/), some of the collected trash images didn't 
contain waste. This was mostly because certain photos were taken at legal dump sites,
which weren’t clearly marked during data collection.

One of the main issues was that the data collection process didn’t include any form 
of tagging to specify whether an image contained waste, whether it was a legal or illegal dumping site,
or if there was any visible trash at all. This lack of metadata posed a challenge for filtering 
and interpreting the dataset effectively.

To solve this, I decided to build a simple web application that can automatically
detect whether an image contains trash. The purpose of this tool is to assist in 
post-processing the mapping data by tagging images based on the presence or absence of visible waste.
This step helps to clean up the dataset and make it more useful for further analysis, decision-making,
or public awareness campaigns.


The result application can be found [here](http://trash-detection.herokuapp.com/).

Once the tool was ready, I ran it on the full set of collected images. The results were visualized through an interactive [web app](http://dar-trash-viz.netlify.app). You can explore these insights by navigating to the
`Analysis` menu and selecting the `Trash Tagging` option. This section provides a breakdown of how many images 
were flagged as containing waste versus those that weren’t, as well as other related statistics.


In terms of performance, the tool achieved a rough accuracy of about 60%, meaning that 6 out of every 10 images were correctly tagged in
terms of trash presence. While this is far from perfect, it's a useful first step toward automating the cleanup and classification of 
large image datasets gathered in the field.

Going forward, I plan to improve the [tool](https://github.com/ResilientDar/trash-detector)’s accuracy and possibly incorporate manual review options or allow users to
contribute to labeling images. This could help create a more reliable and scalable system for waste detection in mapping projects.

If you're interested in contributing, testing the tool, or sharing feedback, feel free to get in touch!]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Making of Trash Data Visualization</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Trash-Map/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Making of Trash Data Visualization" /><published>2018-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Trash-Map</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Trash-Map/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/trash_map.png)

_Online Trash Map_

In August 2018 [HOT](https://www.hotosm.org) together with [Nipe Fagio](http://nipefagio.co.tz) organized waste data collection activity, allocating more than 
100 students/mappers to locate and collect information about the types of piles in the Dar es salaam City.

The aim of this activity was to raise awareness to the responsible institutions for waste management about the importance 
of data-driven decision and policy making and also to showcase how waste data can be used to measure and evaluate the 
waste collection problem in Dar es salaam.

The activity resulted into collection of more than 10,000 waste piles. After the activity the HOT team presented the 
data to  [TURP](https://www.worldbank.org/en/programs/tanzania-urban-resilience-program) program.

As part of TURP team, we analyzed the data and built a web map that visualized and provide important insights for the 
nearly 10,000 points. We used [Mapbox GL JS](https://docs.mapbox.com/mapbox-gl-js/api/) together with a [React](https://reactjs.org/) framework, these enabled creating a 
vector based web map that has high rendering performance and a smooth user interaction.

The trash web map can be accessed [here](http://dar-trash-viz.netlify.app) and source code for the map [here](https://github.com/ResilientDar/dar-trash-viz/).

## Insights

The web map serves as an example of how spatial data and geospatial technologies can be leveraged to bridge the 
gap between available waste-related data and effective policymaking. The current waste management challenges in Dar es Salaam
pose a significant obstacle to the city’s aspirations for urban development. Ensuring the availability and accessibility of 
reliable waste data is a crucial first step toward addressing this issue.

By enabling data analysis, such tools offer the ability to conduct informed and calculated assessments of main problems, 
thereby supporting evidence-based decision-making. One particular insight from the map is the 
high concentration of waste disposal sites in and around the city center—areas characterized by dense population,
increased human activity, and vibrant local economies.

Such insights can reveal underlying behavioral patterns related to waste disposal. Once identified and analyzed,
these patterns can inform solutions that are grounded in actual data, thereby increasing the likelihood of resolving
the main challenges.

Moreover, the web-based map infographics indicate that many of these waste accumulation points are accessible 
by vehicles or carts, suggesting that targeted cleaning and maintenance activities are feasible. 
This accessibility further supports the potential for sustained cleanliness and improved waste management 
in these areas.


## Future

Addressing waste collection challenges in Dar es Salaam through data-driven approaches, it is essential
to incorporate a broader range of metrics and analyses. The city must recognize and integrate economic, environmental,
and social indicators to develop comprehensive and sustainable waste management solutions. This multi-dimensional 
perspective is key to achieving a cleaner and more livable Dar es Salaam and other developing countries cities with
similar challenges.

The trash map aims to inspire other partners and stakeholders to support and invest in data-centric waste management 
technologies. Tools like these play a critical role in highlighting the severity of the current waste problem and 
can drive informed actions toward meaningful change.]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Developing Twaamtaro (Adopt a Drain)</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Twaamtaro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Developing Twaamtaro (Adopt a Drain)" /><published>2017-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Twaamtaro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Twaamtaro/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/twaamtaro_logo.png)

## Twaamtaro Tanzania

Online platform that tracks local drain cleanliness & information on solid waste deposits.
Inspired by Adopt a Drain from Code for America!.

### Background
Waste cleanness in Dar es salaam drains is rarely done, and when it is done, there is lack of dissemination of the work and drains status to respective leaders and stakeholders. There is always a need to raise community engagement in drains cleaning and to find innovative ways that can enable provision of reports on drains cleaness to the community.

### Leverage

Community mapping project ‘ramani huria’ has collected the available data on the drainage network. These are available and  can be  found on openstreetmap, these data shows that the network has not covered the large part of the city and from different reports it is not frequently maintained in the areas it has covered. More details can be found [here](http://ramanihuria.org/mapping-drainage-in-dar-es-salaam/)

Building on this work, arrangements were made to organize the community to frequently clean these drains so as to help water flow especially on flood prone areas, this went in parallel with development of application to monitor, store and show drains information called Twaa mtaro (Adopt a drain).

Twaamtaro as a platform enables the community to report about cleaness activities that are done on drains, it does this by letting users send drains information through SMS, USSD and WEB, this enables even the average citizen who does not have access to the Internet to be able to use the platform.

The workflow is citizen are assigned drains by the street leaders, they receive SMS notification from the platform, when the finish cleaning they can send SMS or use USSD or login into the online twaamtaro site and update the status of their drains.


![Twaamtaro in action](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/twaamtaro_in_action.png)

_Twaamtaro in action_

![Me presenting Twaamtaro to World Bank Tanzania Staffs](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/twaamtaro_pres.jpg)

_Samweli (Team lead) presenting Twaamtaro to World Bank Tanzania Staffs_

[Source code](https://github.com/Samweli/twaamtaro)

[Platform](https://twaamtaro.org)]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Isochrone Maps Creation in QGIS</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Isochrone-Maps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Isochrone Maps Creation in QGIS" /><published>2016-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Isochrone-Maps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Isochrone-Maps/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/isochrone_map.png)

_example isochrone map showing hospitals accessibility times in minutes by car_

## Isochrone Map

Isochrone maps are a powerful way to visualize accessibility and movement within geographic areas.
Unlike traditional maps that focus on distances, isochrone maps illustrate the areas that can be reached 
from a specific location within a given amount of time—whether by walking, driving, cycling, or public transportation. 
These maps are particularly useful in urban planning, emergency response, transportation analysis 
and public service delivery.

For example, a city planner might use an isochrone map to evaluate how many residents can reach a health facility within
30 minutes by foot or to identify underserved neighborhoods based on commute times to the nearest school.

At the time of writing this post, there were limited options available for creating isochrone maps using open-source tools.
Most services that offered isochrone generation were either commercial, limited in functionality, 
or required API keys with usage restrictions. Additionally, QGIS( a free desktop GIS application) did not natively support
the generation of isochrones, which presented a barrier for many users interested in spatial accessibility analysis
without relying on proprietary software or paid APIs.

Recognizing this gap, I created a QGIS plugin to enable users to generate isochrone maps 
directly within the QGIS environment. This plugin extends the functionality of QGIS by allowing users to easily define
origin points, provide travel networks, and generate accessibility zones using open routing services. It simplifies a process
that previously required external tools or manual steps, making it far more accessible to planners, researchers, and civic
technologists who rely on free and open-source GIS software.

One of the core goals in developing the tool was to make it completely open source, so that it could be freely used, 
adapted, and extended by the broader GIS and open data community. The plugin is hosted publicly and available for download,
with full documentation and source code accessible [here](https://github.com/Samweli/isochrones).

Since its release, the plugin has received a strong reception within the QGIS community. As of August 2019, 
it had been downloaded over **7,000** times from the official [QGIS plugin repository](https://plugins.qgis.org/plugins/isochrones/#plugin-versions),
highlighting the demand for accessible isochrone tools within the open-source GIS ecosystem. 
These numbers continue to grow as more users discover its capabilities.

The plugin is a contribution to the broader mission of opening access to geospatial analysis tools. 
By lowering the barrier to entry for isochrone mapping, it empowers individuals and institutions especially 
in resource-constrained settings to better understand, enable data based decision-making and 
improve accessibility in their environments.

### Links

[Plugin repository](https://plugins.qgis.org/plugins/isochrones/)

[Source code](https://github.com/Samweli/isochrones)]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Developing Flood Maps</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Flood-Maps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Developing Flood Maps" /><published>2016-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Flood-Maps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Flood-Maps/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/flood_map.png)

## Floods in Dar es salaam

Dar es salaam is one of the fastest growing cities in Africa, it has a 5 million population and 5.6% percent 
growth rate per year, it is also the most important economic center in Tanzania. This indicates
that the city should undertake all social and economical preparations effectively accommodate population growth.
	
However, for the past years the city has been overwhelmed by the growth rate of the population leading to inadequate 
public services provision, unequal resources sharing such as water, electricity and a dormant urban infrastructure. 
The latter being the major cause for the recurring floods in the city.

As the city continues to expand, much of the new development has occurred informally and without adequate planning.
This unstructured urban sprawl has placed huge strain on the road network and drainage systems, making mobility
increasingly difficult. During the rainy season, poorly planned settlements—often built in flood-prone areas, makes
the situation more difficult by blocking natural water channels, further contributing to the severity and frequency of
urban flooding.


### Floods Map Tool

In relation to the flood problem in Dar es salaam, I made an effort to help the society in reporting of the 
floods events, believing this will enable measuring floods impact and foster robust response during raining seasons.

An online flood map, Inspired by [flood map india](https://osm-in.github.io/flood-map/), a tool
that shows flooded features in realtime as reported by map users, this is crowdsourced based effort to map 
inundated features in Dar es salaam.

In response to the flooding challenges in Dar es Salaam, I took the initiative to support the community by 
developing a tool aimed at improving the reporting of flood events. I believe that by enabling timely and accessible 
flood reporting, it will make it possible to better assess the impact of flooding and support more coordinated and effective
responses during the rainy seasons. Collecting such data from those directly affected offers crucial insights into the 
severity and spread of floods, helping both authorities and communities prepare and respond more efficiently.

To bring this vision to life, I developed an online flood mapping platform, inspired by the [flood map india](https://osm-in.github.io/flood-map/) project. 
The tool allows users to contribute real-time updates about flooded areas using a crowdsourced approach. 

Similarly, the Dar es Salaam version of the map empowers residents to report inundated roads, neighborhoods, and key 
infrastructure in real time. By relying on contributions from the public, the platform builds a dynamic, community-driven 
picture of flood conditions across the city.

This tool serves as both a public awareness and a practical response aid. It helps identify flood hotspots 
as they occur, enabling faster decision-making for rerouting traffic, allocating emergency resources, or issuing alerts.
Over time, this kind of community mapping can also support long-term urban planning by highlighting areas that require 
drainage improvements or other interventions.

The flood map is a step toward participatory resilience building. 
By involving citizens directly in disaster response, it strengthens the relationship between the public, 
urban planners, and emergency services, paving the way for a more informed and resilient Dar es Salaam.

[Link to the Flood map](http://samweli.github.io/flood-map/)]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Code for Resilience</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Code-for-Resilience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Code for Resilience" /><published>2016-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Code-for-Resilience</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Code-for-Resilience/"><![CDATA[![Code for Resilience Dar es salaam kickoff](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/code-for-resilience.png)

## Code for Resilience Dar es salaam

Dar es Salaam and Stone Town are the two primary cities of Mainland Tanzania and Zanzibar
with populations of 5.5 million and 150,000 respectively. Each of these cities and their country
have unique challenges and natural hazards. Dar es Salaam for instance is challenged by bi-annual flooding,
impacting many thousands of its citizens every year. In response to this, the World Bank, GFDRR, 
Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team and the Red Cross are supporting the Tanzanian Commission of Science and Technology,
Buni Innovation Hub, Dar es Salaam City Council, Ardhi University and the University of Dar es Salaam
with a community mapping for flood resilience project, Ramani Huria. 

In coordinating all of these actors, Ramani Huria has leveraged the skills of over 100 community members,
150 students, collecting data in the most flood prone neighbourhoods of Dar es Salaam, making maps and
underlying data freely available for Dar es Salaam.

In 2015, Ramani Huria, in collaboration with the World Bank, had the opportunity to host the [Code for Resilience](https://understandrisk.org/initiative/code-for-resilience/#:~:text=Code%20for%20Resilience%20(CfR)%20fosters,risks%20posed%20by%20natural%20disasters.) 
program in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. This initiative aims at bringing together local talent, international expertise, and
community knowledge under one roof with a shared goal: to develop innovative tools that address the real challenges
posed by natural disasters in a specified region.

As part of the World Bank team, I supervised the Code for Resilience fellows and mentored them. 
Each of the fellows was assigned a problem statement (project) from which they had to design and implement a solution. 

Each of these projects and others were initiated on January 30th 2015, via a collaborative event at the Buni Innovation Hub in Tanzania, 
the event brought together Code for Resilience Fellows from the University of Dar es Salaam, 
experts from the Dar es Salaam City Council, and local developers. 
This initiative aimed to develop tools that enhance disaster preparedness and community resilience. 
Among the projects initiated were the automation of population statistics delivery and the creation of 3D-printed 
weather stations using recycled plastic, reflecting a commitment to sustainable and accessible technological solutions.

One significant project from this event was the development of the [WorldPop API](https://github.com/codeforresilience/worldpop-api), designed to facilitate access to 
population data. This tool allows users to query area population statistics from the WorldPop dataset, 
providing valuable insights for planning and response strategies in disaster-prone regions. 
By automating the retrieval of demographic information, the API supports informed decision-making and 
efficient resource allocation during emergencies.

Another key project was the [Weather Dashboard](https://github.com/codeforresilience/weatherDashboard), tailored to provide real-time weather forecasts for Tandale,
a neighborhood in Dar es Salaam. This dashboard offers meteorological data, enabling residents 
and authorities to monitor weather conditions and prepare for potential hazards. The tool exemplifies how 
localized information systems can empower communities to respond proactively to environmental challenges.

These initiatives underscore the potential of collaborative efforts in leveraging technology for disaster resilience.
By combining local expertise with innovative tools, the projects developed at the Buni Innovation Hub demonstrate a 
promising path toward a more resilient Tanzania!


![Team lead interviewed for Code for Resilience Tanzania Program](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/cfr_interview.jpg-large)
_Samweli (Team Lead) getting interviewed for the Code for Resilience Tanzania Program_

[Video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KYnkZE9r0UQ&t=6s)]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Collection of Daladala Routes</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Daladala-Routes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Collection of Daladala Routes" /><published>2016-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Daladala-Routes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Daladala-Routes/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/bus_routes.png" alt="Dar es salaam transport routes (Bus routes in red)" /></p>

<p><em>Map of public transport in Dar es salaam <a href="https://api.mapbox.com/styles/v1/samtwesa/cijptupyz002d94kq81o26eww.html?fresh=true&amp;title=true&amp;access_token=pk.eyJ1Ijoic2FtdHdlc2EiLCJhIjoiZTc1OTQ4ODE0ZmY2MzY0MGYwMDNjOWNlYTYxMjU4NDYifQ.F1zCcOYqpXWd4C9l9xqvEQ#19.3/-6.816097/39.280324/0">link</a></em></p>

<h2 id="dar-es-salaam-transport">Dar es salaam Transport</h2>

<p>Dar es Salaam’s public transport system is primarily built around Daladala minibuses, which form the backbone of daily commuting for the majority of the city’s residents. In addition to Daladalas, the city also operates a ferry service across the harbor, a commuter train, and a modern Bus Rapid Transit (BRT) system known as DART (Dar Rapid Transit), which began operations in 2016 to improve urban mobility.</p>

<p>Back in 2015, as part of the Ramani Huria team, we collaborated with <a href="http://www.door2door.io">ally</a>, a transport and mobility-focused company, on a project to map the entire Daladala minibuses network of Dar es Salaam. This was an initiative aimed at bringing greater visibility and structure to the informal and semi-formal transport system that millions rely on every day.</p>

<p>Our main task was to organize and manage teams of local mappers, assigning them specific bus routes across the city to document. These mappers would ride Daladalas, recording routes and frequencies using GPS-enabled tools. This data collection was essential for building a comprehensive open dataset of the city’s transport network.</p>

<p>The project not only helped visualize the complex web of routes but also laid the groundwork for future urban planning, route optimization, and the integration of digital transport tools. It was one of the early examples in the region of using open mapping and data science to make cities more accessible and livable.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/daladala_mapping.png" alt="Mappers" /></p>

<p><em>Mappers boarding Daladala buses to map routes</em></p>

<p><a href="https://samweli.github.io/dar-bus-tracking">Here</a> is a live demo of the bus route data that were collected, showing the mapping process in action. This interactive map showcases the actual tracks recorded by mappers as they go through different Daladala routes throughout the city — a powerful visual representation of just how extensive and vital this transport network is.</p>

<p>Additionally, we documented the entire project and made the data open for everyone. You can find a detailed overview of the project and its results, on the Dar es Salaam Transport Wiki hosted by OpenStreetMap. This serves as a valuable resource for anyone looking to understand urban transport mapping or to replicate similar projects in other cities.
The wiki for the project can be found here <a href="https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Dar_es_Salaam/Transport">transport wiki</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate Action Hackathon</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Climate-Action-Hackathon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Action Hackathon" /><published>2016-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/Climate-Action-Hackathon</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/Climate-Action-Hackathon/"><![CDATA[![](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/undp-hackathon.jpeg)

## The Last Mile
That was the buzzword for the hackathon carrying a meaning that after all the years of collecting, organizing and storing climate data, 
it is now time for technology to make use of them and provide cutting edge applications.

The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) launched this for the application developers to create new 
web or mobile applications that serves weather data in areas trying to adapt to climate change in the region.

Under the UNDP programme called Climate Information for Resilient Development in Africa (CIRDA), 
software developers were invited to Livingstone, Zambia to participate in the hackathon.

The developers formed teams to create prototypes, mobile and information-system-based applications and
technological solutions that shares actionable weather and climate information to a variety of stakeholders,
sectors and end-users.

As a result different applications, platforms and proof of concepts prototypes were built, see the full list [here](https://climateaction.io/).

I had a chance to participate in the hackathon, it was wonderful to meet people who have been working on
climate data. There were so much data with variety supplied by different climate change stakeholders,
it was interesting challenge to be part of a group that was working on coming up and building 
useful tools around the gathered climate data.

As part of a development team of four, we collaboratively built [ClimateFrame](https://github.com/climate-action-hackathon/ClimateFrame), a framework aimed at enabling regional
experts to effectively communicate their knowledge with local communities.

The ClimateFrame framework allow regional experts to define and automate actions—such as
sending alerts or messages—based on specific events in live datasets. By bridging fragmented data sources 
with local expertise, it enables the creation of communication systems that inform and protect 
vulnerable communities. 
 
For example, an expert can select relevant datasets, set conditions for 
triggering alerts, and deliver messages via text or ASCII art to subscribed users when certain thresholds are met.
This approach simplifies the process of turning complex data into actionable, localized insights.

![ClimateFrame group working on the prototype](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/samweli/jekyll-now/master/images/climate-frame-undp.jpg)
_ClimateFrame group on action_

#### Other Groups on Action
![cah_image](https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1540/25222387034_ce974f0299_z.jpg)
![cah_image2](https://c7.staticflickr.com/2/1506/25552275070_77cef53b62_c.jpg)
![cah_image3](https://c1.staticflickr.com/2/1466/25552301320_4f17a8f354.jpg)

### Presenting Partners

The CIRDA Programme
UNDP’s Programme on Climate Information for Resilient Development in Africa (CIRDA) supports Climate Information and Early-Warning Systems Projects in 11 of Africa’s Least Developed Countries in their missions to save lives and improve livelihoods. By building capacity to issue extreme weather warnings, sharing new technological advances in weather monitoring and forecasting, and facilitating innovative partnerships with the private sector, the programme works to foster regional cooperation, support strong institutions and build resiliency to climate change. 

The Brown Institute for Media Innovation
The Brown Institute was established in 2012 by a gift from Helen Gurley Brown, long time editor of Cosmopolitan Magazine, in honor of her late husband David Brown, a filmmaker producing works like Jaws and Driving Miss Daisy. The Institute is a bi-coastal collaboration between Stanford’s School of Engineering and Columbia’s Graduate School of Journalism. Its mission is to sponsor thinking, building and speculating about how stories are discovered and told in a networked, digitized world.

The International Research Institute for Climate and Society (IRI)
IRI was established in 1996 by the U.S. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) and Columbia University as the world’s first international institute with a mission to apply climate science in the service of society. IRI uses a science-based approach to enhance society’s capability to understand, anticipate and manage the impacts of climate in order to improve human welfare and the environment, especially in developing countries.]]></content><author><name>Samweli Mwakisambwe</name><email>smwltwesa6@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>